

I am a polymath, empathetic, proactive and pragmatic individual. I like teamwork, however I usually opt for a wide degree of autonomy and time flexibility. I enjoy challenges and I seek them actively. I am currently involved in research, showing special prowess at mathematical modeling and computer programming tasks. I am confident carrying out complex quantitative or qualitative analyses, specially in fields such as applied micro- or macroeconomics, and public policy. Furthermore, as a competent and active social volunteer, I have experience interacting with vulnerable population and designing and implementing social development and educational projects at local scale.

SKILLS

PROGRAMMING

R, Python, Matlab (Octave), Maxima (Mathematica), Stata, ŁTĘX, OTree, Dynare, SAS, PostgresQL, HTML, CSS, Javascript, Microsoft Office, Git.

COMMUNICATIVE

Spanish C2: Native English C1: Proficient German B2/C1: Advanced French A1: Beginner

ACADEMIC INTERESTS

Public Policy
Social Networks
Behavioral Economics
Algorithmic Statistics
Computer Science
Political Economy
Community Socioeconomics
Philosophy of Economics

PERSONAL PROJECTS

Kampagne für Frieden in Kolumbien sos-colombia.de

> Cordillera EV cordillera.eu

Nicolas E. Fajardo-Acosta

nicofajardo@gmail.com · nfajardoa.github.io

EDUCATION

Economics (M.Sc.)

2019 – 2021 Diss. "Scaling Up Preschool Education: A Semiparametric

Estimation of its Effect on Early Learning Outcomes in Peru"

Diss. supv. Prof. Lena Janys Faculty of Law and Economics

Bonn, DEU RHEINISCHE FRIEDRICH-WILHELMS-UNIVERSITÄT BONN

Adv. modules Computational Statistics, Public Economics, Labor Economics, Growth and Development Economics, Banking and Securitization, Behavioral Public Policy. Research emphasis in Applied Microeco-

nomics.

Adv. modules

Economics (B.Sc.)

Faculty of Economic Sciences [FCE]

Bogotá, col UNIVERSIDAD NACIONAL DE COLOMBIA

Post-Keynesian Macroeconomics. History of Biological Thought. Critical Perspectives on Economic Theory. Dynamic Programming. Computational Economics. Project Design, Management, and Evaluation. Economics and Politics of Sustainability. Behavioral Economics. Finance, Crises, and Inequality. Microeconometrics. Advanced Growth Economics. Economic Theory and Policy, Design

Thinking, Epistemology of Psychology.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Short-Term Consultant

10/2021 - 06/2022 Trade and Integration Unit

Supvs. Drs. Isabela Manelici, José P. Vásquez and Román D. Zárate

Development Economics Vice Presidency

Remote WORLD BANK GROUP

 $\hbox{\it Duties} \qquad \hbox{\it Develop algorithms to match highly irregular databases, using a mix of manual matching and}$

regular-expression rules. Support the research process in all its stages.

Research Assistant

11/2019–01/2022 Worked for Drs. Stephanie Majerowicz, Román A. Zárate, Franz Ostrizek,

Armin Falk among others.

Bonn, DEU BEHAVIOR AND INEQUALITY RESEARCH INSTITUTE [BRIQ]

Duties Clean and manage large databases, ranging between 1 and 25 million observations. Implement

and execute multiple estimators of treatment effects using Machine Learning and parallelized algorithms. Complete plots and proofs using Wolfram Mathematica. Review relevant literature on

Economics of Education, Social Networks and Moral Action.

Investments Analyst

01/2019 – 08/2019 Front Office

Supv. Andrés Enrique Rodríguez Arévalo

Investments Department

Bogotá, COL SOCIEDAD FIDUCIARIA DE DESARROLLO AGROPECUARIO S.A.

Duties Analyze the economic behavior of local and international markets. Design strategies and valuate fixed-income investment portfolios. Develop econometric models for forecasting. Write and present

briefing papers and reports, including Daily Market Dashboards. Lead biweekly internal meetings on current macro-financial developments. Communicate with clients, market analysts and traders.

Intern

01/2018 – 12/2018 Economic Policy Studies Department

Supv. Norberto Rodríguez Niño

Office of the Deputy Technical Governor

Bogotá, COL BANCO DE LA REPÚBLICA DE COLOMBIA

Duties Gather, clean, reshape and analyze databases. Implement structural and semi-structural econo-

metric models, such as State-Space representations, VAR and VAR-X. Execute panel data estimators. Develop algorithms for mathematical optimization, web scraping and text mining. Estimate bayesian DSGE models. Review relevant literature on analysis and evaluation of Monetary Policy.

Nicolas E. Fajardo-Acosta

COURSES AND SEMINARS

Participant

01/2020 Basic course on Human Research

Social & Behavioral Research Investigators
Massachusetts Institute of Technology Affiliates

Online COLLABORATIVE INSTITUTIONAL TRAINING INITIATIVE [CITI]

ACADEMIC REFERENCES

Prof. Dr. Phillip Eisenhauer Universität Bonn peisenha@uni-bonn.de

> Prof. Lena Janys Universität Bonn ljanys@uni-bonn.de

PROFESSIONAL REFERENCES

Asst. Prof. Isabela Manelici London School of Economics i.manelici@lse.ac.uk

Asst. Prof. Román A. Zárate University of Toronto ra.zarate@utoronto.ca

Asst. Prof. Stephanie Majerowicz Universidad de los Andes s.majerowicz@uniandes.edu.co

Markus Antony Scientific Manager briq Institute markus.antony@briq-institute.org

PERSONAL INTERESTS

Communal work
Music [Violin & Guitar]
Performing arts
Aerial silk
Poetry and creative writing
Ecological conservation

STATEMENT OF ENGAGEMENT

Beyond researching, I enjoy partaking in different projects and ideas, willing to impact society through rigorous analyses or actions, connect with people and gain valuable insights. Currently, I am a member of Cordillera, a group of Latin-Americans ready to represent fairly and without intermediaries a rainbow of Latin-American identities and values in Europe. Moreover, in 2021 I joined the Campaign for Peace in Colombia. A platform to make the German public and politicians aware of the systematic human-right violations in Colombia. In the past, I managed community development and environment-awareness projects via workshops directed at children and teens living in vulnerable settlements.

Participant

o8/2019 • Micro Data for Economic Policy and Development

o6/2016 – 07/2016 • From Nudge to regulating Uber

Homero Cuevas Seminar

Faculty of Economic Sciences [FCE]
UNIVERSIDAD NACIONAL DE COLOMBIA

Participant

Bogotá, COL

02/2019 – 03/2019 • Territorial Actions on Peace-building

03/2019 – 04/2019 • Participatory Policy-making

District Institute for Participation and Communal Action

Online ALCALDÍA MAYOR DE BOGOTÁ D.C.

in cooperation with

UNIVERSIDAD NACIONAL ABIERTA Y A DISTANCIA

Participant

08/2018 – 09/2018 3th Certificate Course on Informal Settlements:

Impact, Participation & Community development

Bogotá, COL FUNDACIÓN TECHO - COLOMBIA

Speaker

10/2017 "Social innovation & Microcredit:

¿Are we financing the status quo of poverty?" VIII International Public Policy Colloquium: Public Policy Implementation and Peace-building

Bogotá, COL UNIVERSIDAD NACIONAL DE COLOMBIA

Participant

01/2017 • International Financial Markets

01/2017 • Financial Mathematics

Unit of Analysis on Economic Sciences [UACE]

Bogotá, COL UNIVERSIDAD NACIONAL DE COLOMBIA

ENGAGEMENT

Participant

03/2020-09/2021 "Ausbildung als Multiplikator*innen für Bildungsarbeit"

Modules: Water, Climate, Displacement, and Consumption.

Bonn, DEU LATEINAMERIKA-ZENTRUM E.V.

Duties Design multiple didactic resources for school children to address world's current most pressing

 $challenges\ from\ both\ German\ and\ Latin\ American\ perspectives.$

Volunteer

02/2018 - 09/2019 Neighborhood "los Laureles", loc. San Cristóbal

Division of Community Experience

Bogotá, col FUNDACIÓN TECHO - COLOMBIA

Duties Design, manage and evaluate Community Development Projects. Create and implement strategies aimed to enhance abilities and capacities related to Peace and harmonious coexistence between

children and teenagers living in informal settlements. Plan social intervention procedures with vulnerable population. Lead large groups of volunteers on the field. Instruct and inspire new volunteers through structured seminars. Organize, plan and execute large-scale events.

Volunteer

04/2017-04/2019 Environmental Planning

Tenjo, COL ITACA: ESPACIO ECOCULTURAL

 $\hbox{\it Duties} \qquad \hbox{\it Plan reforestation and environmental recovery actions on damaged over-exploited zones. Lead}$

groups of volunteers on the field. Instruct volunteers on how to seed, transplant, and care saplings.

AWARDS AND SCHOLARSHIPS

Scholarship holder

10/2019-09/2021 Scholarship Program for Foreign Students

Bonn, DEU KONRAD-ADENAUER STIFTUNG

Top 10 pct. Graded Average: Economics

08/2019 Undergraduate Degree Earners in 2019-01

Faculty of Economic Sciences [FCE]

Bogotá, COL UNIVERSIDAD NACIONAL DE COLOMBIA

Best score: at National level

12/2018 Reference group: *Economics*

SABER-PRO 2017 "La Noche de los Mejores" Test on the Quality of Higher Education

Bogotá, COL MINISTERIO DE EDUCACIÓN NACIONAL

Participant

08/2018 – Present Seedbed of Talents
Bogotá, col. FUNDACIÓN COLFUTURO

PUBLICATIONS

WORKING PAPER

02/2019 "Inflows of International Tourists to Colombia during 2001-2017:

Evolution, Characteristics and Determinants"

(with C. Agudelo, C. González, E. Montes & N. Rodriguez) BORRADORES DE ECONOMÍA: BANCO DE LA REPÚBLICA N° 1064

MANUSCRIPT

08/2017 "Social innovation & Microcredit:

Are we financing the *status quo* of poverty?" (with S. Espinosa-Moyano & D. Gantiva-Parada) ECONOGRAFOS: ESCUELA DE ECONOMÍA FCE - CID N° 113

April 27, 2022